<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boke entytuled the next way to heuen the whiche in true walky[n]ge or goy[n]nge is but thre dayes iourney, and to go or walke euery daye but thre myles as wytnesseth moyses who sayeth. Ibimus viam trium dierum in solitudinem. [et]c. Exodi. iij. Ca. F.</title>
            <title>Next way to heven</title>
            <author>Peter, of Luxemburg, Saint, 1369-1387.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1520</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849816</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849816</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 139:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boke entytuled the next way to heuen the whiche in true walky[n]ge or goy[n]nge is but thre dayes iourney, and to go or walke euery daye but thre myles as wytnesseth moyses who sayeth. Ibimus viam trium dierum in solitudinem. [et]c. Exodi. iij. Ca. F.</title>
                  <title>Next way to heven</title>
                  <author>Peter, of Luxemburg, Saint, 1369-1387.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the sygne of the Sonne by Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1520?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Saint Peter of Luxemburg, whose name appears in the colophon.</note>
                  <note>Original title not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and address from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁶ C⁴.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14986:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14986:1"/>
            <p>¶ The boke entytuled the next way to heuen the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in true walky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge or goy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nge is but thre dayes Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney / and to go or walke euery daye but thre myles as wytneſſeth moyſes who ſayeth. Ibimus viam trium dierum in ſolitudinem. &amp;c. Exodi .iij. Ca. F.</p>
            <figure/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14986:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han I beholde the eſtate &amp; lyfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue ben of ſyns y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I coude knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good &amp; the yll I ne fynde but ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes &amp; tyme loſte and yf I ony good dedes haue done yet are they not dygne ne worthy of guerdon / for I them haue done ſo neclygently w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out loue &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out aduyſe. And it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth me / &amp; alſo I doubte me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they all ne be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ony thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge worth. Alas ſuche am I wherfore I doubte leſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I be cut downe &amp; caſt in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre. That is to ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I be not after this preſent lyfe put vnto deth &amp; caſt in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre of hel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deuilles &amp; with my ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. Alas I haue waſted of goodes &amp; loſt for to noryſſhe my caryon more than I haue wonne. Certes I am not worthy to be called man or woman / for I haue ledde a ryght foule lyfe &amp; poore. And for as moche I haue ſhame to lyue / &amp; alſo I dare not dye. Alas now ſholde I wepe all the tyme of my lyf for to recouer the tyme that I haue loſt. Alas body ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner what thynkeſt thou / knoweſt thou not wel that one tyme it behoueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to dye / &amp; alſo thou ne knoweſt wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne how. Knoweſt thou not well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudgement of god aprocheth / certes yes. O what anguyſſhe ſhall that be vnto the euyll parſones to ſe a daye full of derkneſſes of ſorowes of trybulacyons / of cryenges / &amp; brayenges of wepynges / and of waylynges / and of dredes of abaſſhe mentes of eclepſes and of thonders / of tempeſt / and of yre / &amp; of other grete &amp; horryble thynges. O y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhal be harde tydynges &amp; bytter. O what heuynes / o what dolour / alas what thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſt thou ſlepeſt thou / or wakeſt thou what abydeſt thou. Alas that thou arte on ſlepe whan thou trembleſt not to here ſo grete thonder. Alas drye tree worthy to be cutte and put in the fyre / tell me
<pb facs="tcp:14986:2"/>haſt thou ony fruyte / ye mayſt thou ſay moche y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>ll and roten / for ſynne is bytter &amp; ſtynkynge. Alas here is an euyll lyfe where as I haue lefte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de mentes of god and haue obayed vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes of the worlde / not vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde all onely / but vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde vnto fleſſhe / &amp; vnto the deuyll. God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> created vnto his ymage / and redemed and gouerned from day to daye. And promyſeth to gyue vnto the his realme / &amp; it is he without whome thou ne mayſt lyue / and alſo thou haſt done vnto hym ſo grete dyſpleaſure wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt not dayned to obey vnto hym / but haſt loued more derly to obey vnto the worlde / vnto the fleſſhe / and vnto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll / A it is no lytell thynge how be it that it ſemeth vn to the ſo. Alas what ſhalte thou ſaye at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iuge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment whan all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme that thou haſt lyued ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded how thou haſt ſpent it. For it hath be lente y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for to employe in the ſeruyce of god thy creatoure. Alas weneſt thou that it be now tyme to go to play to laugh to bourde to ſpeke trifles / cextes nay / But it is tyme to playne and to wepe and to enchaſe &amp; flee from ſynnes &amp; to plante vertues / &amp; to do good werkes. And after this lyfe it ſhall betyme to play / &amp; that is in a fayre delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place. Now proue I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> than that it behoueth to yeld accompte euery houre of euery momente of tyme ſyns that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> were borne tyll vnto thy depatynge. And there at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudgement before god before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyrgyn Marye &amp; aungelles / and all the ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and before all the worlde And there ſhall be ſerched and demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded all that / that thou haſte done ayenſt the wyll of god. And alſo vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhal be ſhewed all the good dedes that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt lefte vndo ne the which thou ſholdeſt haue done yf by penaunce it ne had be pardoned the. And that thou ſhalte be wel ſet</p>
            <p>The nexte waye to heuen.
<pb facs="tcp:14986:3"/>aboute with ſynne / yf thou wepe them not now by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon / contrycyon / &amp; ſatyſfaccyon. And than ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> reknowlege Iuſtyce &amp; mercy and ſo ſhalte reſt for than prayer / ſeruyce / promyſe / force / gyftes excuſacyons ne fayre ſpeche / ne penaunce in no wyſe maye helpe / ne no thynge ben of valoure / &amp; than ſhall theſe ſynners ſe the Iuſte Iudge out of meſure wroth &amp; redy to do Iuſtice without mercy. And vnder ſhall they ſe the depe helles open to engloute them / &amp; more than an hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande tourmentes the whiche be made redy vnto them And on theyr ryght hande they ſhall ſe all theyr ſynnes wherof they ſhall haue meruayllouſly grete hydour / &amp; on the lefte hande they ſhal ſe theſe enemyes horryble &amp; moche cruell in theyr terryble &amp; hydeous fourme awy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge that the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Iudgement be yelded and caſt vpon the ſynners to the ende that thy may drawe them with them in to hell. And alſo they ſhall ſe the tyre enflambed without forth. And alſo they ſhall fele theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne without forth. Alas yf thou be than of the nombre of ſynners what cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> make were mayſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hyde the / the whiche now ne mayeſt here the worde of god / certes in noo parte. But it behoueth the to appere wylte thou or not / &amp; ſhalte abyde the dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſentence. Alas what ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> than do / thou ſhalte than tremble / for now begyn our ſoules to tremble yet dyſpayre the not / but retourne vnto hym the whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt wretchedly offended &amp; pray hym humbly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl haue of the pyte and mercy / &amp; that he wyl gyue the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don. And haue thou good hope in his mercy / &amp; he ſhall receyue the with good wyll / for he receyueth gladly the ſynners whan they retourne towarde hym by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye of penaunce / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche waye hath thre dayes Iourney
<pb facs="tcp:14986:3"/>in lengthe / as ye may here here after in this preſent bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke as ſayth ſaynt Peter of Lucembourgh.</p>
            <p>SAynt Peter ſayth that we ben all pylgrymes in this worlde here. And we walke day &amp; nyght w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our reſtynge in to our countre the whiche is in heuen. And for to haue recreacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as theſe pylgrymes the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſpeken with good wyl in walkynge theyr waye. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in goynge vnto our pylgrymage / that is paradyſe / we ſhall ſpeke alytell / for we walke ſtrongly &amp; we haue not but thre dayes Iourney to walke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one of the ſayd thre dayes Iourney is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trycyon / &amp; the other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon the thyrde is ſatiſfaccyon. And in lykewyſe ſayth Moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes vnto vs. Ibimus viam triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dieru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolitudine. The fyrſt ſholde be contrycyon / that dayes Iourney hathe thre leges or miles from thens to walke. The fyrſt lege or myle is dolour of hert of that / that by his ſynne man hath deſerued the gybet of hell. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de myle is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led dolour of herte of that / that he hathe loſte the grete Ioye of paradyſe. The thyrde mile is dolour of herte &amp; grete dyſpleaſaunce of that / that a man hath offended god. Certes theſe thre myles ſholde be ryght anone go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto a good walker or goer. Example / if a man were taken for ony euyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath done / as yf he had ben take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his thefte &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth &amp; men lede hym vnto the gybet / and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge mette hym &amp; hym de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded frende wheder do they lede the. And he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Syr they lede me to be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged bycauſe I am a the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe. Alſo I haue well deſerued it for the euylles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue done. And the kynge anſwered vnto the thefe. I haue pyte of the / &amp; yf thou wylte promyſe me that thou ſhalt do no more ſo as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt done in tymes paſte &amp; that thou
<pb facs="tcp:14986:4"/>be ſory of that thou haſte deſerued to be hanged I ſhall delyuer the. I byleue that he ſholde be ryght Ioyefull So ſholde he be anone at the fyrſte myle. And other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample how a man ouercomen amonge theues the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue robbed hym of his goodes / and is lefte poore. And in that the kynge meteth hym &amp; hym demaunded Frynde how is it with the. And he anſwereth ryght yll for I haue ben robbed and haue loſte all my good. And the kynge ſay the vnto hym / frende be thou ſory of that that thou haſt loſt thy goodes and I ſhall yelde it the &amp; yet more he ſholde be more gladde than before. That is to ſaye that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner ſholde be ſorowfull of that / that he hath loſt paradyſe by his ſynnes. Now may ye demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de me &amp; ſaye / ye ſaye that coutrycyon yeldeth agayn all the goodes. And I haue loſt my vyrgynyte / how ſhall contrycyon yelde it me. Frende I anſwere the that yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue loſt two grotes or two nobles and yf Iyelde vnto the agayne ſyxe thou haſte well recouered thy loſſe. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample a maſer of marbyt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is broken hath loſt his beaute in his ancyente / but it may be in ſuche wyſe made agayn that it ſhall be more dere than before by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> golde &amp; the ſyluer wherwith it ſhall be anourned. And ſo I ſay the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf thou haue loſt thy vyrgynyte the beau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of thy vyrgynyte ne may be recouered / but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſte ſo repayre it &amp; aourne it by ſo noble vertues that it ſhal be better &amp; more rycher than it was before. Example of Magdaleyne and of Marie egypcyen the which them anourned ſo well and of ſo noble vertues ſo rychely that they were more worthy after tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before. Be thou than ſorowfull of that that thou haſt loſt thy vyrgynyte &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodes of grace &amp; paradyſe ſhal be yelded vnto the as it is ſayde. And this is the ſconde myle of this Iourney.
<pb facs="tcp:14986:4"/>And other example / a clerke ſerued a byſſhop y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſholde gyue hym a benefyce / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd clerke lefte his ſeruyce of the byſſhop / &amp; yode to ſerue an other mayſter and loſte the loue of the byſſhop. And than the byſſhop ſayd vnto the clerke / thou haſt wrathed me / but yf thou wylte be ſory thou ſhalte haue my loue as thou haddeſt before / &amp; I ſhall gyue the the benefyce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I haue promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to gyue the / ſholde not he be anone ſory of that I by leue that yes. And in lyke wyſe is it yf thou wrath god by thy ſynne thou ſholdeſt haue contricyon &amp; make thy peas. And oure lorde ſhall gyue vnto the the realme of paradyſe. And this is the thyrde myle of this Iourney &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of that here ſholdeſt thou make thy gyſte &amp; reſt the / but it ſuffyſeth not to be ſory of that / that thou haſt euyll done and that thou haſt deſerued to be in hell ne of that / that thou haſte loſt paradyſe / but for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / that thou haſte loſte the loue of god thy good lorde. Example yf thou haſte wrought with Peter and whan the euen tyde ſhall come thou goeſt vnto Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to demaunde thy wages / &amp; Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall anſwere the. My frende he with whome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haſt wrought ſhall paye the thy wages &amp; not I. Haſt thou not herde ſaye / who ſo ſet the to werke let hym paye the. And in lyke wiſe may god ſaye at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth of the man in Iudgement of hym / the which ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t onely for the drede of hell and for the loue of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radyſe to haue it all onely &amp; ſhall ſay my frende go thou in to hell and take there thy rewarde for thou lefteſt not for to do the euell for the loue of me / but witout more for the drede of hell / where our lorde ſhall ſaye / ſpeke vnto hell that he helpe the and ſocoure the / yf he may / for I am not holden to helpe the at thy nede for thou ne haſte done the good dedes that thou haſte done for the loue of
<pb facs="tcp:14986:5"/>me / but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt done them for to haue paradyſe all onely &amp; for drede of hell / &amp; ſo than y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt doo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good dedes for to gete the loue of god / and not for drede aboue all of thy dampnacyon. And ſo go thou the thre myle aboue ſayed / &amp; ye ſhall reſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of the thyrde. That is to ſaye that he ſhold be ſory of that / that he hath deſerued to haue hell and loſt paradyſe / but in eſpecyal aboue all thynges ſory of that / that he hath loſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god by his ſynne. A man ſholde ſeke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trycyon entyerly ſo that he maye fynde it. And after to haue the loue of god his creatour. And not to do as dyd the man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which abode to confeſſe hym tyll vnto the dethe / &amp; than he cryed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trycyon contrycyon wheder are ye gone. And ſoo he ne myght fynde it &amp; knowe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that it was true Iuſtyce of god. For ſaynt Gregory ſayth. It is good reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god forgyte hym or her at the deth / the which in his lyfe en helth forgyteth god &amp; leueth. Repent we than in as mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as we ben in good helth &amp; in lyfe &amp; god ſhall pardon vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good wyll / and it is the fyrſt Iourney</p>
            <p>THe ſeconde Iourney of paradyſe is confeſſyon. Fewe people can wel walke that Iourney with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out goynge out of the waye / And it is no meruayle / for how maye he be a good clerke the whiche ne goeth / but one tyme in the yere to the ſcole / and yet ryght well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſed ne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete payne may he be a good werke man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche hath his crafte. The good clerke ryſeth vp for to ſtudye by nyghte / and in lyke wyſe ſholde we doo for to lerne this ſcyence. And in lyke wyſe dyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Dauyd as it is ſayd in the pſalter. Media necre ſurgebam. I aroſe vp ſayd he at mydnyght for to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my ſynnes / for to aduyſe me whan I ſhall goo to
<pb facs="tcp:14986:5"/>confeſſe me. That is ayenſt thoſe the whiche go to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion without aduyſe. The ryght entre of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon is I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe me vnto god / vnto the vyrgyn Marye / &amp; vnto al the ſayntes of paradyſe / &amp; vnto you ſyr y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche are in goddes ſtede &amp; vycayre. This fyrſt worde I confeſſe me cloſeth hell vnto the ſynner &amp; openeth vnto hym pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche was ſhette vnto hym by his ſynne &amp; ſo hath peas with god and ſhetteth the mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preeſt werof men rede vnto that purpoſe an example.</p>
            <p>A Ryche man fader of the curate of the towne ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vilany vnto a poore man / &amp; the poore man ne myght venge hym preſently / but taryed tyll that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che man yode vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feldes for to ſe his cornes al alone and the poreman y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſe hym come toke the coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of his ploughe &amp; ſlewe the ryche man. And after he yode to lede his ploughe / &amp; noo man wyſt who it ſholde be. Afterwarde a great whyle it hapned that the poore man had repentaunce of his myſdede &amp; yode to confeſſe hym to his curate the whiche was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſone of the ſayd ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che man that he had ſlayne. And as he ꝯfeſſed hym the curate apperceyued well that he had ſome ſynne in his conſcyence that he durſt not tell / wherfore he ſayd to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> My frende hardely tel all thy ſynnes / for there is none ſo great but that god may well pardon after that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym requyre mercy / &amp; alſo in that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I may I ſhall hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe the &amp; I ſhall pardon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. And than ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore man, Ha ſyr I am the curſed man the whiche hath murdred your fader ſo by ſuche maner / &amp; for that cauſe I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe vnto god and vnto you ſyr in requyrynge pardon and abſolucyon. Than the preeſt chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged his blode for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / but he ne made no ſemblaunt and pardoned vnto
<pb facs="tcp:14986:6"/>the good man with good herte the deth of his father / &amp; after ward the curate ſhewed vnto the poore man grete token of loue more by halfe than he was wonte in ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his wyfe apperceyued it well / &amp; ſo hym demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by many tymes what it was to ſaye that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curate cometh ſo often to ſe the / &amp; that he vnto the ſheweth ſoo great token of loue. And ſo oftentymes hym demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that he tolde her and compted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trough wherin he dyd as a fole. Now it happened y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he was wrothe wyth his wyfe and wolde bete her. Than ſhe eſcryed hym &amp; lepte in to the myddes of the ſtrete &amp; ſayd in cryenge out / out the thyfe the murdrer he wolde ſlee me as he hath done the fader of our curate. And than the chyldren &amp; paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed man whan they herde that / that ſhe had ſayd they ranne all with pykes &amp; ſwerdes for to ſlee the poore man. Whan he them apperceiued he lepte haſtly vpon a mare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had &amp; fledde. And in fleynge he mette the curate comy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge on horſbacke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche came to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the towne &amp; ſayd vnto hym / my fayre ſone how is it with the / wheder gooſt thou ſo haſtly / &amp; the poore man tolde hym ſhortely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe wherfore he fledde. A ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curate my frende come downe frome thy mare anone &amp; lepe vpon my hors which goeth more ſwiftly to thende that thou mayſt eſcape fro my parentes the whiche fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the. Than the poore man lepte vpon the curates hors and fledde. And that hangynge his frendes came the whiche folowed the good man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſayd vnto hym. A fals traytoure you haue wel hyd the murdre of your father &amp; he hath tolde it you in confeſſyon. A fayre lordes ſayd the curate ye haue wronge who hath tolde you ſuche thinge I knowe no thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / but I knowe wel that he is one of the good and well dyſpoſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this
<pb facs="tcp:14986:6"/>paryſſhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And they anſwered velye / ye knowe it well / but ye haue euer more hydit vnto vs. And yet now haſt thou taken vnto hym thy hors for to eſcape frome vs &amp; from our handes / and alſo ye haue taken his mare the preeſt excuſed hym euermore and alſo excuſed the poore man / &amp; ſo moche that they were wrothe with him in ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wyſe that they ſlewe the ſayd curate / &amp; ſo ye ſe wyll by thys example how this worde I confeſſe me cloſeth the mouthe of the preeſt. Now ye ſhall here wherfore a man ſaith vnto god almyghty vnto the bleſſyd vyrgin Mary and vnto all ſayntes. The reaſon is ſuche. Our lorde hathe two courtes / the one is of Iuſtice &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other of mercy. And the deuyll dare not lay hande on the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner tyll vnto ſuche tyme that he be delyuerd vnto hym And the deuyll cometh vnto the courte of Iuſtyce for to accuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore &amp; myſerable ſynner. And Iuſtyce anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth. I byleue the not for thou arte a lier. Than anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth the deuyll. I haue good wytneſſes dygne of fayth &amp; of credence without ony reprofe / that is to knowe all the trynyte of paradyſe / the vyrgyn Marye &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſayntes / and his good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell before whome he hath done his ſynnes / but for me they ne wyll come hyder / wherfore call ye theym your ſelfe / &amp; than whan Iuſtice calleth god / our lady / all the ſayntes in wytneſſe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell &amp; fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it is that it is ſo as the deuyll ſayth yf ye haue not ynoughe of wytneſſes I cal his owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcyence. And I you praye that ye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iure hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaye trouth / &amp; than Iuſtice ſeeth by the counſeyle of the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that it is ſo. And ſo is it truely I ne can excuſe me. Than ſayth Iuſtyce vnto the ſynner ſyth that it is ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god / our lady / the ſayntes / &amp; thy good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel with thyn owne conſcyence haue of accorde that thou haſte done
<pb facs="tcp:14986:7"/>mortall ſynne / &amp; that in this ſynne thou arte deed with out repentaunce thou ſholdeſt be dampned perdurably for the wytneſſe that the deuyll bryngeth forth by ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent / &amp; it behoueth that I caſt ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of dampnacyon vpon the pardurably / for god ſayth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete. Ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>que peccauerit ip<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a moriet<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That is to ſaye / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule the whiche hath ſynned ſhal dye &amp; ſhall be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned. So I ne knowe what counſeyle to gyue but onely to appel vnto the courte of mercy / &amp; put the and al thy cauſes in her hande. Than the ſynner ſholde appel vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courte of mercy the whiche is in this prenſent lyfe / &amp; he ſholde go haſtly to confeſſe hym. And fyrſt he ought to call the grace of god / for the enemy ſhall purſewe hym &amp; theder ſhall ſende .iiii. aduocates &amp; ſhall make partye for to let this confeſſyon. And euery man ought to vnderſtande in this wyſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe hym &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courte of mercy. The fyrſt aduocate that the deuyll ſendeth ayenſt the ſynner that is curſed angre or diſpleaſure to tel his ſynne / and ſhall ſaye in this wyſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner. Tell thou not thy ſynne it ſholde be grete ſhame vnto the / yf men knowe that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte done ſuche vylayn outrage &amp; abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / vnto the whiche aduocate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner ſholde anſwere I ſhall tell it &amp; dyſcouer purely and makyngly &amp; large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without ony thynge hydynge for it is wryten who ſo couereth his ſynne god ſhall dyſcouer hym at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemyes / before the vycgyn mary and aungelles / &amp; ſayntes / &amp; before all the worlde. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this aduocate ſhall be in ſuche wyſe vay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quyſſhed than ſhall come the other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche hath to name ypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryſye &amp; ſhall ſaye thus / tell it not vnto thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſour for he weneth that thou be a good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; yf thou tell it hym he ſhall take his herte from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / &amp; he ſhal neuer ſet gretly
<pb facs="tcp:14986:7"/>by the. Byleue not ſuche an aduocate / for it is fals / for knowe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that all good confeſſours loue better y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner or the ſynners after the confeſſyon than before / &amp; for as moche as he confeſſeth hym of the more grete ſynnes &amp; abhomynables of as moche loueth hym the better / as ye haue hyrde here aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſours be of the nature of aungelles / for as moch as the aungelles ſeen a more grete ſynner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted of as moche make they the more grete Ioye in henen / as our lorde ſayth by the euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſtes &amp; alſo the confeſſours. Example by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell the whiche ſpeketh of one the whiche had an ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred ſhepe wherof he had loſt one he left the .iiij. ſcore &amp; .xix. &amp; yode to ſeke that whiche was loſt / &amp; whan he had fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hym he toke hym bytwene his armes &amp; bare hym in to his hous ſayenge vnto his frendes and neyghbours make Ioye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me / for I had loſt my ſhepe &amp; now haue I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Inlyke wyſe it is of god whan he fyndeth agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the ſynner by true confeſſyon he maketh more grete Ioye &amp; feeſt than he dyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iiij. ſcore Iuſt. Yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylte be than happy &amp; well loued of thy confeſſour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the hardely &amp; dyſcouer thy ſynne playnly / purely / &amp; clenly. And he ſhall comforte the &amp; ayde the / &amp; ſhal ſhewe more grete good of the than before. And whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte vayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyſſhed this aduocate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll theder ſended the thyr de that is hope or truſt of longe lyfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſhall ſaye My frende thou arte yet yonge / thou ſhalte confeſſe the tymely ynough. Unto whome thou ſholdeſt anſwere I ſhall confeſſe me ſhortly / for I haue no ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rte of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. And whan he ſhal be in ſuche wyſe vay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quyſſhed Than ſhall come the fourth aduocate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is curſed drede to do grete penaunce / &amp; ſhall ſaye in ſuche wyſe / tell not thy ſyane for that / that it is to moche grete / yf thou tell
<pb facs="tcp:14986:8"/>it he ſhall gyue the ſo grete penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that thou he mayſt do it / ſo ſholdeſt thou be worſe than y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> were before / vnto whome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte anſwere. Salomon ſay the who ſo dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to do a lytell penaunce &amp; to ſuffre he ſhall haue ſoo moche to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there is no tonge the whiche can tell it for it behoueth that the ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es be puniſſhed or elles where. Than tell all thy ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es / for yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hyde ony ſynnes by the counſeyle of ſuche an aduocate thou leſeſt thy cauſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courte of mercy / &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> tell all y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte quyte / &amp; to ſe the ſo quyte that god ne our lady ne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes whiche ben in paradyſe / ne the deuyll that is in hell ne yet none other thynge ſhal neuer haue in my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ne haue remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy myſdedes / ſo ſayth god by the pyhete yſaye. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recordabo amplius iniq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatis ſue. Than ſhall y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſynner be well happy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche dare tell his ſynne vnto a man mortal the whiche is a ſynner as he is whan in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other worlde before all the courte of paradyſe it ſhall be vnto hym in reproche yll aduyſed ſhal he be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche loueth better to be in horryble penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; torment in all tymes perpetually tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be there one yere or two. or .v. or .viii. or x. or .xx. yf thou haddeſt woundes mortelles &amp; thou ne ſheweſte but .xj. to the ſurgyon / the .xj. ſholde be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and the .xij. ſholde be roten / and ſholde make therin thende to dye. In lykewyſe ſhall do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> leueſt to tell &amp; ſhall rote thy ſoule hydynge the thou ſhalte dye ſpyrtually by that poynt. Now haue ye hetde whefore men ſaye I confeſſe me vnto god / vnto the bleſſyd byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn marye / and vnto all the ſayntes of paradyſe / and vnto you ſyr. Now ſhall ye vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that this Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney hath thre myles as the other hath. The fyrſte is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the confeſſyon ought to be entyer as it is ſayd without ony thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hydynge. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ought to be made
<pb facs="tcp:14986:8"/>of good wyll without conſtraynte as Dauid ſaith. Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie ſacrificabo tibi et co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fitebor. ¶ The thyrde is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſynner haue a very fayth and a truſt that god hym may pardon / for as ſaynt Auſtyn ſaith. God is more re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy to pardon vs than we ben to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym pardon And in thende of his mile the ſynner may reſt hym and take hoſtell and not in the other two. That is to ſaye to reſt in eſparau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to haue pardon &amp; not to do as dyde Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>das y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſayd I haue ſynned in betrayenge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy blode Innocent &amp; Iuſte. He ꝯfeſſed hym voluntayrly &amp; entyerly his myſdede &amp; made ſatyſfacyon for he yelded agayn the .xxx. pens. But he yode not by this later my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le for he diſpeired hym. And ſo dyde Cayn whiche ſayd My ſynne is more greter than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of god. But he ſholde haue ſayd. My ſynne is moche grete / but yet is the mercy of god more greter / and tho he cryed to god for mercy &amp; he abode the grete mercy of god and he had mercy and ſoo had Iudas. Now haue ye hyrde the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coude Iourney / now here ye the thyrde⁂⁂⁂</p>
            <p>THe thyrde Iourney to walke in to paradiſe is ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſfaccyon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche Iourney a man may not come thyder. This Iourney hath thre myles as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other hath. The fyrſt is to reſtore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theft y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man hath done / for ſaynt Auſtyn ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is not pardoned tyll that the thefte be reſtored. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dimitter<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> petm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> niſi re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtituatur ablatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who ſo than taketh from an other hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behoueth to yelde it / and alſo who ſoo taketh from god ony good ſoule &amp; withdraweth it by ſynne or by his yll example it behoueth hym to yelde it and to reſtore it.</p>
            <p>Or who ſo taketh frome ony his renome / &amp; areyſeth yll grace it behoueth to reſtore hym vnto his good renome
<pb facs="tcp:14986:9"/>Now may ſome ſaye. I am yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; I ám ledde by coyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſe wantoneſſe as moche as I may / &amp; I haue ſhende my ſelfe in the chyrche &amp; in many other ſtedes &amp; places before men / &amp; women ſo moche that many hath ſynned by my folyſſhe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce / werof I haue be culpable by many an yll example or by my draught how may I with drawe them from ſynne / for I ne knowe them all And alſo yf I ſholde retourne towardes them parauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture they ſholde be enflambed in ſuche maner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhold retourne vnto ſynne or that themſelfe there myght fall agayne more ſtrongely. And therfore me ſemeth that it ſholde be grete peryll to retourne towardes them / and what ſhall I there doo than / ye ſholde take from ſynne thoſe or them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue made to ſynne / that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt ſure &amp; beſt / but yf ye may not put you in payne to with drawe other / &amp; to yelde them vnto god for to put them in the place of thoſe that thou haſt taken from hym / ſo ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> appeaſe him. For yf ye haue taken from a man fyue ſhyllynges / it is not of neceſſyte that I yelde vnto hym agayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe fyue ſhyllynges yf I ne may fynde it / but it behoueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye yelde vnto hym other fyue ſhyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges. And for as moche as thou knoweſt not how ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny people thou haſte drawen vnto ſynne / therfore thou ſholdeſt put the in payne by good examples &amp; by good doctrynes to retracte &amp; withdrawe as many people as thou haſt made to ſynne / yf thou ne mayſt mo conuerte vnto god &amp; elles yf thou ne mayſte conuerte the people by wordes or examples at the leeſt praye for them often in goodnes. Example yf a kynge made a noble dyner &amp; made to crye ouer all that who ſo ſholde haue &amp; brynge the greteſt company ſhold be beſt welcome &amp; alſo ſholde haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt fayreſt gyfte / euery man ſholde paye him
<pb facs="tcp:14986:9"/>to come to dyner &amp; to brynge the mooſt of people of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght for to haue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt gyfte. And in lyke wyſe is it of god for our lord hath made a crye ouer all the worlde by his meſſengers that be the apoſtles / the prophetes / &amp; the doctours / &amp; by the predycacyons that he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſhall brynge the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt fayreſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany vnto dyner that is to knowe mooſt ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les vnto paradyſe by his examples &amp; doctryne he ſhall be mooſt beſt beloued &amp; vnto whome god ſhall do mooſt grete honour. And alſo in ſo doynge y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte do honour vnto god yf thou payne the ſo to do &amp; praye often god in ſayenge. ¶ Syr / or lorde wylte thou by thy grace enlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myn my herte &amp; myn vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may haue eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry day reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy paſſyon &amp; gyue me knowlege in what maner I may lyue for to drawe mooſte ſoules vnto the. And alſo that I may lyue vnto thy prayſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche it maye be vnto the ſaluacyon of my ſoule and of many other. Alſo who ſo hath wretched an other it behoueth to appeaſe hym / &amp; to crye hym mercy &amp; to aſke pardon / and alſo thou ſholdeſt reſtore the good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome &amp; good fame vnto hym to whome thou haſt done yll by thy curſed ſpeche. And yf it were ſo that ony had taken ony goodes temporall by ony curſednes the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che worldly goodes &amp; temporal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde gyueth better and by more ſtronger reaſon the good ſpyrytuall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god gyueth they ſholde well better by reſtored And y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt demaunde how a man maye that reſtore. Where that a man ne may one worde brought forth drawe backe but that it abydethe ſpoke. I graunte me vnto that / but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne ſhalte neuer be quite tyll vnto that / that with all thy puyſſaunce in all maners that thou canneſt and mayſt thou hym haſte reſtored / and that thou haſt ſayd vnto
<pb facs="tcp:14986:10"/>all thoſe &amp; vnto all them the whiche by the cauſe hathe ſynned or ſhall ſynne in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thynge ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt lyed / &amp; that thou haſt made them ſo to byleue. And for thoſe thou ne knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche it may byleue thou arte hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the chyrches to pronounce it in ſayenge that the wordes that thou haſt ſayd vpon ſuche a perſon be not true / and that thou ne knoweſt neuer ne yet ſaweſt but good in hym and that curſedly thou haſte pronounced it ayenſt hym / and that it ne was but for to blame hym and ſoo ſhalte thou haue the fyrſte lege or myle. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde myle is to wepe and to complayne his ſynnes / or to do almyſdede or penaunce / or other good dedes for to haue pardon &amp; ſoueraynly for the loue of god. And that ought to be done by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſeyle of his good confeſſour. And the thyrde myle is to pardon vnto thoſe the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath yll ſayd vnto you or myſoone. Now may ſome ſaye how maye I pardon hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche hath done me domage &amp; without cauſe &amp; reaſon. And yet alſo they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue mocked me before the ſtretes / &amp; yet I ne dyde neuer dyſpleaſure vnto them. Example yf there were aman that ought vnto the kynge a thouſande pounde / &amp; the kynge helde hym in pryſon &amp; ſayd vnto hym / yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> paye me not thou ſhalt be hanged / and he had not wherof to pay. And yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge wolde ſaye vnto hym ſuche a man there is that oweth the .v. ſhelynges / &amp; I ſhall gyue to the that thou oweſte me &amp; I ſhall let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> go quyte &amp; thou ſhalte be my ryght welbeloued / &amp; yf thou do it not thou ſhalte paye me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou oweſte me / or I ſhall make the to be hanged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out remedy / ſholdeſt anone do it I byleue that yes. And yf he dyd it not men wolde ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he were a foole. In lyke wyſe is hit ſpyritually to ſpeke / we ben gretly indetted ayenſt the grete kynge that is vnto god
<pb facs="tcp:14986:10"/>And it behoueth that we paye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto hym that that we owe hym / or we ſhall be hanged on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gybet of hell / but yf the kynge wyll do vnto vs grace ſayenge pardon all that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men hathe myſdone vnto you / certes we therto ſholde well accorde for we haue a hundred thouſande ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes more myſdone vnto god than man hath done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. And therfore ſhold we with ryght good wyll par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don &amp; ſo haue ye herde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre Iourneys the whiche it behoueth to haue to entre in to paradyſe wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner hathe ſo moche done by the grace of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is that he be in the eſtate of grace than ſholde he kepe hym aboue all thinges to fall agayne &amp; to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye the better kepe hym he ſholde take in hym a maner of lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge how he wyll lyue / &amp; alſo to abſteyne hym from ſynne / in lyke wyſe as he maye wel knowe that whan he doeth ſynne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it diſpleaſeth god. And ſo he pleaſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is a grete folye. And fyrſte thou ſhalte praye for the chyrche &amp; for all the prelates of the chyrche &amp; for all pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the erth / &amp; for all the people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte vnto hym. Afterwarde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte praye for all thoſe vnto whome thou arte holden. And after for al creatures the which ben in trybulacyon ſoueraynly for thoſe that ben departed and deed vnto whome we ben holden / &amp; thou ſholdeſte thynke on the euylles of thy ſelfe. And on the glorye that thou woldeſt haue / and on the paynes that thou haſt deſerued. And after on the houre of dethe and on the houre of Iudgment. And go often vnto the chyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che and with good wyll / as ſoone as thou arte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage of Ieſu chryſt where he is crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied / and after take holy water / and knele on thy knees and begyn to ſaye. Veni creator ſpiritus me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes tuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or Pater noſter / and after take thy ſete in the chyrche
<pb facs="tcp:14986:11"/>the mooſt pryuy place that thou mayſt. And after thou ſhalte ſay pryme / houres / and the letany / in ſayenge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for gete not the paſſyon of thy creatoure in ſayenge thy houres / &amp; at euery maſſe that thou hereſt ſaye thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteor ſoftely &amp; all the tymes that it ſhall be feeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thou ſhalte be at the hye maſſe &amp; at the euenſonge and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the vnto the ſaynt of whome the feeſt ſhall be / &amp; the remenaunt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feeſt employed in good werkes ſpyrytuall. And y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the vnto a confeſſour the whiche hath ſcyence &amp; that he be a man of good conſcyence / for yf he hath thought on his owne ſoule he ſhall haue thought of thyn / &amp; yf he be ſuche as I tell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obey vnto hym in all goodnes as vnto the vycare of god be thou not ydle at no tyme ne yet ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> before thy dore in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrete ne yet in thy windowe / be thou more often alone than in company. And as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to faſtynge made by good dyſcrecyon y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is moche good &amp; that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out diſcrecyon it is nothynge worth vnto hym the whiche faſteth / ne yet almeſdede without dyſcrecyon is noo thynge worthe. And in lyke wyſe as a lampe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out oyle ne may haue lyght / euen ſo is faſtynge &amp; almeſdede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out dyſcrecyon / &amp; thou ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt knowe that the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> draweſt in to thy body thou oughteſt to gyue it for the loue of god vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore / and with that it behoueth to eſchewe fro ſynne / or that ſholde be the faſt of the deuyll the whiche alway faſteth &amp; euermore doeth yll thou ne ſhalte ete but two tymes on the daye yf thou be not ſeke / &amp; ete thou neuer tyll that thou haſt ſayd benedicite before / and after gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces / and ſpeke but lytell at thy dyner yf it be not of god yf thou ſpeke there ydle wordes than repente the. And ſpeke y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> neuer wordes of an other that thou woldeſt not
<pb facs="tcp:14986:11"/>that a man ſholde ſpeke of the. Thou ſholdeſt ſpeke at thy dyner or thynke of ſom good thynge to thende that thy ſoule maye fede as wel as thy body / &amp; whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſayd graces thou ſhalte goo into thy chambre &amp; there y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte ſaye noon. And afterwarde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte ſtudye ſome good mater or exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple / ſpeke as lytell as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt in ony place where ſo y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be for a man ne may lytell ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſynne. Go in to the towne as lytell as thou mayſt. And whan thou haſte there to do / &amp; yf men areſon the ſpeke in brefe &amp; humbly and retourne in to thy hous as ſoone as thou mayſt / ete but litel oute of thy hous be thou py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore people yf thou wylte that god take the in good gree &amp; that he haue pyte on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyue often for the loue of god after thy power y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſte. Yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue ony thynge to do whiche toucheth the do it by the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeyle of a good perſone. And alſo thinke that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ne mayſt nothynge hyd from god ne kepe / but that he ſeeth all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalte do and ſaye. Ordeyne ſo well thy conſcience that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalte be ſeke that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne haſt no cauſe but for to thynke on thy creatour. And towarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euentyde thou ſhalte ſaye euenſonge &amp; vygylles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed yf thou can them &amp; paſſe not the daye but that thou thynke one tyme of the daye on thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence in recordynge thy ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes for to holde the in humylite &amp; thou ſhalte knele and ſalewe the holy trynyte / &amp; thou ſhalte ſay at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leeſt thre tymes the pater noſter / &amp; after ſalue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyrgyn Marye and reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the vnto god &amp; vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgyn Marye and make ſome good prayer vnto thy good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell that he be thoughtfull to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / &amp; after bleſſe the &amp; take ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly water &amp; laye the downe &amp; ſlepe in ſome good thought Be thou often in orayſon be it of mouth or of herte ſaye thynges brennynge to haue deuocyon. Thre thynges
<pb facs="tcp:14986:12"/>there ben the whiche ayedethe to haue deuocyon. The fyrſte is puryte of conſcyence / in lykewyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan ony wolde pray a grete lorde he ſholde take hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan he cometh before hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nothynge appere vnto hym that ſhall dyſpleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. And ſo is it who ſo wyl go in oray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon he ought to eſchewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ne haue ony ſpotte of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſholde dyſpleaſe vnto god the whiche ſeeth the hertes of all the other. Than ſaynt Bernarde ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the tymes that we go in orayſon we entre in to the courte of heuen in the whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge of glory is. Alſo aourned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mayny au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles of princes celeſtyalles and of the gloryus quene of heuen. So we ſholde appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in grete reuerence &amp; in grete fere &amp; in grete humilyte and in grete puryte &amp; in grete cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of herte / to thende that nothynge appere in vs that ſholde dyſpleaſe vnto ſo grete a lorde as vnto god / for ſaynt Iohan ſayth that whan thou makeſte orayſon make that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be ſuche as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ought to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche hath to ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god / purge than thy conſyence of all thynges vnto thy power &amp; meke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / &amp; afterwarde make vnto god requeſt or elles y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt not be exalted. The ſeconde is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he oughte to ſeke a place ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ne be ſeene to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ne be troubled. And that the wynde of vayne glory ne take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruyte of his orayſon. Example we haue in Ieſu chyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che enlonged hym &amp; wente ferre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his dyſcyples wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wolde praye in the gardyn of olyuete / &amp; moyſes the whiche aſſended in to the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne. And alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Marye alone whan he ſaluted her / &amp; ſaynt Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cys had of cuſtome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan he wolde praye god he yode ſerre of in to a wood that his felowes ne myght here hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And of that haue we an example of oure ſelfe / yf a man hath to ſpeke with an other he ſpeketh vnto hym more
<pb facs="tcp:14986:12"/>gladly whan he fyndeth hymſelfe all alone. The thyrde thynge is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houre caſt out of his herte all dremes &amp; thoughtes &amp; afterwarde to be all in orayſon. The .iiij. thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he oughte to haue with all his herte grete entende to praye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt that he gyue vnto hym grace of deuocyon / for orayſon without deuocyon hath no ſauour / put than payne to houe it do that / that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is &amp; god ſhall ende it. And yf god gyue the grace for to worſſhyp hym menynge the payne that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> there ſhalt take wepe / for teeres ben as ryght good wyne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule deuoute wexeth dronke vnto god in orayſon in ſuche maner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ne can refuſe hym in that thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth / in lykewyſe as it appereth by ſaynt Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / and by magdaleyn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which wepte &amp; god gaue vnto them that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that was pardon of theyr ſynnes. Teres ben of ryght grete profyte and of ryght grete v<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>tue / for one only tere maye gete of god that that all the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles in heuen ne all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaintes of paradyſe ne may do that is to knowe whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner wepeth for his propre ſynnes wherof it is wryten in the pſalter that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſacyfyce that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynner may make vnto god is that he be contryte &amp; repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te &amp; that he hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble hym before god in wepynge / for whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tere of the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner repentaunt is offred vnto god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> humble herte &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoute it thrughe perceth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heuen by her vertue &amp; mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth tyl vnto the throne of the mageſte dyuyne / &amp; there ne is aungell the whiche it may ne dare holde tyll vnto that that it be come before the face of god / &amp; that it hath goten that that he wyl for his ſoules helth / for the oray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon the whiche is made in wepynge as ſayth ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyn thrughe perſeth the herte of our lorde Ieſu cryſt &amp; moueth him vnto pyty &amp; entreateth &amp; enclyneth to loue
<pb facs="tcp:14986:13"/>hym &amp; chaungeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of Iudge &amp; recordeth the ſynner perfytely vnto god. The .vj. is that he ought to regarde the eſtate of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t myſery where there is ſoo many perelles that there is none y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche maye it accompte / for man is euermore in temptacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe of worldly vanitees / and of the begylynge of of thyn enemy / other in ſtepinge or in wakynge / or in ſpekynge But he ſholde thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worlde &amp; the fleſſhe ne vayn quyſſhe but theyr frendes / &amp; therfore ſholde he wel kepe hym that he ne be frende of the worlde ne of the fleſſhe / for all thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue the worlde and the fleſſhe ben the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myes of god as ſayth ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Iames. Meruayle it is how the worlde may be Ioyous who ſo well regardeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll of this worlde / for the worlde is a Iayle wherin we ben in pryſon for our ſynnes / &amp; we ne knowe whan we ſhall goo out of it wheder we ſhall be ſaued or dampned Now ſholde it be agrete nouelte yf the theſe ſholde ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge or laughe whan men lede hym to be hanged / but yet ben we well more out of wycte and more abuſed than ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che theues for we renne all vnto the gybet of hell &amp; vnto dampnacyon perdurable all daunſynge and makynge feeſt / for we ben in lyke wyſe as a veſſel in the hye ſee w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the ſayle ſtretched &amp; hyſed with wynde at wyll &amp; we go euery daye on grete Iourneys to warde hell or para<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyſe / for we ne knowe yet in what parte we ſhall aryue &amp; ſo all in ſlepynge / in walkynge / in drynkynge / in etyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge in playenge / &amp; in ſingynge euermore we goo for war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out areſtynge as people the whiche ben of the ſee. And therfore who ſoo well beholdeth this worlde &amp; the grete peryll he ſholde haue better cauſe to wepe than to laughe / for yf the ſynner beholde the heuen he ſeeth the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree &amp; herytage eternal where as is perfyte felycyte
<pb facs="tcp:14986:13"/>from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he is yet ferre of by his ſynnes. And for as moche he hath good cauſe to wepe. And yf he behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the erthe he ſeeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater wherof he hathe be made and where vnto he ſhall retourne at the houre whan he ſhall departe from this worlde / that is in thende of this lyfe. And yf he loke vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe he ſeeth hel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is redy to engloute hym with mouthe open / and to tour ment for his ſynnes. And yf he loke on the ryght hande he ſeeth the proſperitees &amp; the rycheſſes wherof all the worlde it is abuſed &amp; deceyued &amp; drawne vnto dampna eyon. And yf he loke on the lyfte ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de he ſeeth the ylles &amp; trybulacyons that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed done vnto the good. And yf he loke behynde him he ſeeth the tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath loſt in vanytees &amp; in thoughtes that he ſholde haue diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in good werkes. And yf he loke before hym he ſeeth the deth whiche cometh / &amp; yet ne knoweth wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall dye / ne of what deth / ne in what place / ne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what eſtate. And yf he loke within hym he ſeeth his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence ful of ſynnes / &amp; his wytte &amp; his body full of curſed maners / &amp; enclyned in curſed cuſtomes. And yf he loke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hym he fyndeth hymſelfe enuyroned &amp; beſet aboute with ſoo many perylles / &amp; ne knoweth how he ſhall eſcape. And alſo he ſeeth &amp; knoweth the dure &amp; harde ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ryghtfull Iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhall alſo caſte at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynners of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he is one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre yf he amende not his conſcyence. We ſholde put our ende in teres &amp; in penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; we ſholde call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt in orayſons that he be vnto vs in ayde &amp; that he defend vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all our ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es &amp; from all our myſeryes. The .vij. thynge is to regarde the eſtate wherin he ſhal be at the deth whan all our membres haue loſte all theyr force &amp; ſtrength / &amp; the ſoule goynge forth frome the body ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:14986:14"/>ſe our lorde out of meaſure wroth with hym for his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / yf he ne be than truely penytent &amp; repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of all his defautes / &amp; vnder he ſhal ſe hel open for to engloute hym / &amp; his ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes he ſhall ſe on his ryght hande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhall accuſe hym &amp; the enemies on the lefte hande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which wolde bere hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye &amp; horryble ſhall crye vpon hym. Thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke than often on theſe thynges &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ende and I knowe well yf thou vnderſtode them that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt deſpyſe lyghtly all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vanytees of the worlde &amp; ſhall drawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnto deuocyon / for the vanytees wordely ſhall more greue at the deth than ne do ayde &amp; than there no ne maye ayde ne ſocour / ne frendes / ne parentes / ne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / ne moder / ne almeſdede / ne penaunce / ne prayer of ſaynt holy man or holy woman / ne good dede what ſoo euer he be / ne other thynge yf he be taken in ſynne mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call / than euery man ought well to praye god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll gyue hym grace to leue well &amp; to doo well to put therto payne for good lyfe ledeth to good ende. And ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyn ſaych / who ſoo hath well lyued ne ſhall not dye yll. The .viij. thynge is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ought to regarde &amp; to recorde the grete humylyte and pacyence &amp; the paſſyon of Ieſu chyrſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had in erth for to gyue vs example / for all be it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he were lorde of heuen &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe / yet wolde he be borne for vs of a woman &amp; wolde be poore &amp; deiecte &amp; to ſuſtayne ſo many perſecucyons and payne that a man ne can nombre it / &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houre that he was borne tyl vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre that he dyed on the croſſe he ne wolde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no rycheſſe / ne none honour / ne ony delyte / but euer more had payne trauayle &amp; pouerte. And i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gyueth vnto vs cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyle that he whiche wyll go vnto god ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de more loue in this worlde tribulacyon than delyte—for delytes nouryſſhen the vyces &amp; ledde the ſoule in to hell
<pb facs="tcp:14986:14"/>And therfore a man ſholde deſyre for to be hated of the worlde / for our lorde ſayth / ye ſhal be well happy whan the worlde ſhall hate you &amp; curſe you &amp; ſhall repute you for nothynge. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iudgement ſhal co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me he ſhall ſay vnto thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche in ſuche wyſe hath be mocked in the worlde / ye be thoſe the whiche were w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me in the worlde in theſe temptacyons &amp; therfore come ye with me / for your rewarde is grete in heuen. Praye we than god that he gyue vs &amp; ſende vs tribulacy on in this worlde &amp; gyue puyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to bere it. The .ix. is that he ought to regarde how Ieſu chriſt dyed for vs ſhame fully and with grete confeſſyon / &amp; how he was for vs be ten / ſpytte on / bounde / mocked / and crowned with thor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes the whiche entred in hym vnto the brayne. And ſo in all his paſſyon to recorde that he vnto vs ſhewed mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re greter pacyence / ne more greter loue / ne myght noo man ſhewe vnto his frende than to wyll dye for hym / wherof ſaynt Bernarde ſayeth. Yf my herte were a ſee of teres &amp; myn eyne fountaynes &amp; all my heres ſtremes &amp; all ranne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ceaſynge as a ryuer / ne neuer ceaſed ne fayled / yet ne myght I ſuffycyently wepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſyon of our lorde Ieſu chryſt that he ſuffred for me. The ten thynge is that he ougte to faſten his herte and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyen of his vnderſtandynge to beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ioyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath apparayled vnto thoſe the whiche loue him &amp; he ought to haue in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templacyon the bleſſed &amp; gloryous virgyn Marye quene of all the worlde enuyroned &amp; ſet aboute withe aungelles / &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> archau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her noble couent of virgyns all clothed &amp; anourned ſo rychely &amp; ſo nobly that herte ne maye thynke partye of the leeſt beaute of her vyrgyns. And there ben the prophetes / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles / the martyrs / and the confeſſours the whiche ſhal be all
<pb facs="tcp:14986:15"/>as kynges &amp; prynces &amp; gretelordes and after the other ſayntes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out nombre. O how that they ſhall be ryche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeen. And that it ſhall be grete gladnes &amp; Ioy to ſe the ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany. But what ſhal it be to ſe after warde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge his mayntayn &amp; his eſtate whoſe beaute is ſo grete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all the enhabytauntes of heuen ne maye neuer ynough meruayle ne them fulfyll to beholde hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Saynt Bernarde ſayth that the beaute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges &amp; the beaute of the noble heuen is ſo grete that yf a man were aſſured to lyue in this worlde here a thouſand ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res euermore yonge Ioyous in grete honour &amp; in gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te rycheſſe &amp; with that that he were aſſured to haue all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delytes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he can thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke / yet ſholde he put all thoſe thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as nought for to ſe without more one onely hour of the leeſt Ioye or beaute that is in beuen. There is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> arber of delyces / there ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonges melodyous / there be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the louers varytable there ben the dyſportes pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t There is all that herte may remembre for perſone to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyce. There is glory perpetuall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out honger &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out amenyſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Make we vs redy than haſtely for to go thyder. Ryght dere bretherne &amp; ſyſters aboue all thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / regarde wel yourſelfe / regarde what ye lately haue be / &amp; what ye ſhal be after your deth from whens ye come &amp; wheder ye go and where ye be. Thynke you what it is of a man or a woman after the deth / for it is but a caryon ſtynkynge and foule and mete vnto wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Thynke often that ye ne be but a poore worme all naked goynge forth of the erth and that vnto erth it be houeth you to retourne. Remembre you frome daye to daye / or from one houre vnto an other in peryll to deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de &amp; to fall into hell for our ſynnes ye go vnto the dethe and vnto Iudgement as at an houre. Remembre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye
<pb facs="tcp:14986:15"/>haue be ſent in to the worlde &amp; thynke &amp; remembre you wherfore and what ye there ſholde do &amp; where ye ſhall go to lodge the fyrſt nyght after that we ſhall be depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from this worlde / for ye ſhall go into paradyſe in to purgatory / or in to hell. And yf ye goo in to paradyſe ye ſhall be aſhamed yfye be not as well anourned with vertues as thoſe that ye ſhall there fynde. And yfye go in to purgatory charged with ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es ye ſhall ſuffre the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re payne ryght horryble. And yfye go in to hell ye ſhall haue there ſhame &amp; payne perpetuall horryble &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayllous more than man ne may ſpeke. Be ye than ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyled &amp; certayn that ye ſhall dye / and more ſooner than is ne thynke or wene. The dayes of man be ſhorte &amp; alſo paſſe ſodeynly as the ſhadowe. Be ye certayne that all that ye founde in the worlde it behoueth you to leue ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſes / honoures / delytes we ne ſhall bere noo thynge from hens / but our good dedes and our yll. And in lyke wyſe as thoſe the whiche leue now ben ſo hath thoſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the whiche ben deed. And in lyke wyſe as thoſe the which ben deed were wonte to lyue / ſo ſhall thoſe dye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche now lyue. Loke well vpon this thynge and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue yourſelfe in a wayete / for ye ne knowe the houre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dethe. Lerne to be humble and debonayre. And bere all tribulacyons &amp; aduerſytees ſwetely and in pacience for the loue of god the whiche ſo moche hath borne for you. And eſchewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde as moche as ye may in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges worldely / ſerue ye thoſe the whiche ſerue god / and haue ye none affyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in thoſe the whiche take gladly of an other &amp; the whiche receyue with good wyll gyftes for gyftes blynde the wyſe wen / but haue affyaunce in hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in whome is loyalte for in all maner ſeke your helth Be he with good wyll in the company of thoſe the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:14986:16"/>loue god ſo ye ſhall parte with your good dedes / but kepe you from the hauynge of to moche grete familya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte with man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all be it that he be good or that it ſemeth vnto you that he be good / for many in ſuche wyſe hathe ben deceyued do ye well vnto the poore ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally vnto thoſe the whiche loue god / lerne the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dementes of god and breke them not for no thynge that maye be. Be you euer a true ſayer &amp; verytable and lye thou not for no thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that may come therof / yfye haue to ſuffre for to ſpeke veryte your rewarde ſhall be more grete in heuen. And y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte gyue vnto all people good example. Here euery daye maſſe yfye maye / be ye often in orayſon / and more of herte than of mouth / brefe oray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons perſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heuen / ſo that it be ſayd with good herte ne praye thou thynge the which is not neceſſarye vnto body or vnto ſoule. Drawe all perſonnes vnto good by good doctryne / thynke often on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſion of Ieſu chryſt and deſyre to ſuffre for the loue of hym / in lyke wyſe as he hath ſuffred for vs / flee the temptacyons that ye ne may goodly vaynquyſſhe or ouercome. Be you ſobre in dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynge &amp; in etynge that is the helthe of the body and the welfare of the ſoule / ſeke euermore the peas of god / yf al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde ſholde be worth / for a man ne may pleaſe god and the worlde togyther / and yf ye fall out of good purpoſe goo haſtly vnto confeſſyon / what thynge that ye ſe or here tourne all vnto the beſt / and yf your enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon come to effecte thynke that god doeth it to aſſaye you / or the enemy for to tempte you and for to deceyue you / yf you holde you wel ye ſhall do vnto god pleaſure and yf ye fall yet aryſe agayne by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon as ſoone as ye may in humblynge you / and purpoſynge to amende you au other time / yf the temptacyou come agayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:14986:16"/>you and that ye haue the vyctory loue ye and prayſe ye god / and bere ye amyable that the yll that men hath donne vnto you or ſpoken. Repreue all ylnes that men ſpeke vnto you or do by good maner without wrathyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge you. Be ye contrarye vnto thoſe the whiche ben con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye vnto god and vnto reaſon / and vnto all good ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte / loue you that god loueth / &amp; flee that thynge that god hateth / haue ye peas with all perſones / and ſyke in all thynges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god / purchaſe vertues in doyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge good werkes to thende that ye may come vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye perdurable⁂</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Here endeth the boke of ſaynt Peter of Luce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bourth other wyſe named the nexte waye to heuen. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prynted at London in Fleteſtrete at the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne of the Sonne by Wynkyn de Worde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14986:17"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
                  <head>W C</head>
                  <head>Wynkyn de Worde</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14986:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
